welcome to meditating with john viveki
we do this live stream every weekday
morning at 9 30 am
eastern with mondays alternating between
a new lesson dharma day
and a review of the whole ecology of
practices which we
call papaya day will probably mean
skillful means
uh if you're joining us for the first
time you're welcome um but a lot has
gone on
and so for previous lessons and sits see
the description
i recommend you immediately do lesson
one keep meeting with us
and do the following lessons perhaps one
or two a week and you will catch up and
integrate with us
um in no time i would ask all of you to
please help me to help as many people as
possible
by liking this stream to increase its
visibility on the youtube algorithm
at the end of every session there is q a
please limit those questions to the
psychology of practice this entire
course
for more broad or encompassing questions
please come
to our live stream general q a which
will be
which is every third friday of the month
at 3 p.m
eastern time okay so i think that's it
for today uh let's get into the practice
um and then we'll have some time to try
and get through uh
several questions uh afterwards
so make sure you're in your basic
seated position uh turn your phones on
to do not disturb
and we will begin when i say begin and
we will begin with chanting and then we
will go into the silent sit
okay begin
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
begin your silent set
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and community
perhaps by reciting the five promises
all right so we have some time for some
questions
what kind of meditation or wood or can
concentrated playing music this is from
uh gunter applet great to see you again
winter
for me to what readily comes to mind is
it would be most like
the moving naiji um the reason i say
that is because
as i think i've mentioned this before
the verb in chinese you don't do
or practice tai chi it's the same verb
as playing music you play tai chi
and so i think that concentrated playing
of music would be very very similar
uh to the kind of moving mindfulness
practices you see in things
like lucuna
gaps things that i think
aspect of myself that has been left
unaddressed
due to time and fate and negligence on
my part
is i never developed a music capacity
even though i have a great love for
music um
nietzsche's statement that life would be
his life would be a mistake without
music has always resonated
notice the metaphor resonated very
deeply with me
um so john russon in his book
bearing witness to fit uh to epiphany
and that's and he presents that as sort
of our primary way of being in the world
think about that
bearing witness to epiphany his main
claim is that
all of intelligibility all the patterns
by which we make sense
have a musicality to them the way
they're patterning
and shifting and opening up in our
experience
and part of what it is to be spiritual
is to wake up to hearing
that musicality again and of course
playing actual music
and therefore just like doing actual tai
chi chuan
uh permeates out into the patterns of
your life and wakes you up
and sensitizes you to things and that's
part of what's called ki
or chi like that playing music can wake
you up
and sensitize you to the musicality of
the presenting of being itself
um and i think that
that remembering that deep remembering
was captured in the old metaphor
originally the myth
of hearing the music of the spheres um
i think that's very very central and so
i i i encourage you to keep doing that
and
try and make try and make it a resonant
bridge try and see how much of the
mindfulness you can bring into the music
and then see how much you can let uh
what's happening in the music
generalize and permeate into your life
in general to a way of being
a way of being with things a deeper kind
of
resonance
uh dimitar good to see you again does it
stand to reason that your ability to
learn from your inner sage goes hand in
hand with your ability to trust other
people
especially if the sage is represented by
a person you know
yes um so our ability
to trust other people is
it it's it's code like here's your
ability to trust people
and here's the degree to which you know
yourself and they're co-defining and
co-determining
and co-affording and so to agree to
which your inner sage
helps you to know yourself is the degree
to which you're more capable of trusting
other people
however let's be clear about what that
knowing yourself means i have known
thyself here
because it comes from socrates as
christopher moore argues
really uh powerfully in his book uh
socratic knowledge
knowing yourself is not uh grasping your
autobiographical story
um it's not just your it's not it's not
something that's introspective it goes
with a lot of what i've been saying
about
how you know you're doing well in your
practice knowing yourself is
aspirational
that that your true self is the self
that you are aspiring to in so far as
you are undergoing
a reciprocal opening and transformation
of how the world is disclosed to you and
how you are
finding yourself to the world think of
the self more as the deepest pattern
of resonance rather than as some inner
uh secluded space that is
absolutely self-enclosed and
self-existent
like some sort of god um
so degree to which you are knowing
yourself
in the socratic sense the degree to
which you're the sage
is guiding you and affording you on the
way
is of course the degree to which you can
trust other people when the person who
is your inner sage is someone you know
you need to take care with that it's
it's it's a valuable thing i've had i've
met such a person a
very wise person who was there for me
and guided me through a very
tumultuous and damaging period in my
life um
but you need to it's always important to
not rob them of their humanity
so we know what it is right
we know what it is to put somebody up on
a pedestal um and you have to be careful
about that
uh because um
taking taking that away from somebody
taking a rap taking away their humanity
their mortality from them
um it will um
will ultimately sow
into your inner sage the seed
of dehumanization
you don't want you don't ever want and
this is
why i have difficulty when religions
and i'm not i'm expressing a difficulty
here i'm not looking at like a
a criticism that's attempting to refute
anything no i'm not i'm not i'm not
trying to do that
but when the sage is elevated
as superhuman supernatural the problem
is you sow the seeds
of dehumanization if you're
internalizing that sage
and that sage is not human
not fully mortal you are
you are sowing the potential seeds of
your own
uh dehumanization your own
attempts to be something other uh than a
mortal
and that can carry danger with it now
you might not be doing any of that
dimitar
everything might be going great you
might have a very resonant
and personally connected and mutually
um human connection with this person
who's your inner sage and that's
wonderful
and blessings to you i think that's
fantastic
um but um
i just wanted to say that the answer to
your question is a deep yes if we
understand the sage
as an aspirational kind of
self-knowledge is that affords
an ability the more you are this is what
matters shows right the more you have a
deep
and true connection to yourself the more
you're able to connect to others those
are
determining and if that's the
aspirational self then that will afford
trust
but be careful when the sage is
a a person you know uh because
um there there is a danger
uh there's a danger there there's a
danger it's a general danger
um of removing
the humanity from this age i suppose
this is why christianity always tried to
keep the two together in some kind of
profound
paradox um that jesus was both truly and
completely divine
and truly and completely human and um i
i've never quite understood how that's
supposed to mean but i i understand a
little bit
how they're trying to counterbalance the
very um
the very concern i'm expressing to you
dimitar so i hope that was helpful to
you that was long but i hope that was
helpful to you
kavar what's your opinion on meditating
after consuming
cannabis i've been uh asked this
question before
and um i understand why it keeps coming
up
uh because we are seeking the means
for a transforming uh consciousness
transcending ecocentrism
and as many of you know i advocate for
a return to the use of such disruptive
strategies and acute
including psychedelics but i always
supplement that strongly with the point
that any psychedelic or even
psychoactive
substance has to be put
within a sacred setting
now you you may you may be saying well i
am i'm taking cannabis and then i'm
putting it into the mindfulness practice
and i get that
the difficulty there is
we have a phenomena that's deeply part
of how human memory works it's called
encoding specificity
you never because the self is that
interface
you never just store
the information that you're paying
attention to you're also storing the
entire context to some degree
encoding it in including the context of
your own mental state
uh so i i related i think this already
but i'll just repeat it
you know you do this you give a whole
bunch of people
a bunch of things a bunch of words to
remember list of 50 words for example
and they they get taught them in room a
and then you come back after a week and
you put right or you're sorry
that's too long like you wait about an
hour you come back
and you divide them half of them are in
room a we divide them randomly half them
are now in roommate and half a room b
and you ask them to remember
all the words the people in room a will
reliably remember
more of the words than the people in
room b because
they have not only stored the words they
stored the room and when the rooms match
they remember more
this is why when you're sad you tend to
remember many more sad things than happy
things
so it's difficult for you when you're
sad to remember happy things
now what does that translate to
so one of the guiding principles of this
practice is that meditation is not a
vacation from your life is
an education for your life if you're
smoking cannabis you're getting into a
state
right and encoding specificity that will
not generalize to your
life in general very well those patterns
won't generalize
so generally if you look for example in
in other wisdom traditions indigenous
traditions
um ethnogens like uh psychoactive
substance psychedelic substances
are used sparingly in ritual context to
try and give people
a a a transformative glimpse
of what's possible for them it's not
made
sort of an everyday practice or thing uh
precisely because it should be used in
that ritual context
and it right uh for such a maybe you'll
allow me such exposure
uh to an aspirational future whereas
when you're doing your daily practice
you should be trying as much to set up
patterns that's why i emphasize movement
and an ecology of practices
that will generalize to your life in
general
so i hope that's helpful to you i hope
that's helpful to you
uh dean rouble good to see you again
dean
is it common to have a burst of
emotional anxious energy after an
insight
and notice what seems an emotional
rebound revenge of the monkey mind brain
stem amygdala that's great
after such a deep deepening opening
experience perhaps the vestiges of
reciprocal nerring
on my addiction control yes very much uh
i think
everything you said there is a plausible
account of what's going on
um generally when i mean you know sort
of intellectual insights usually don't
have that thing but i
i get what you're talking about here
dean you're talking about existential
insights
um and so remember that existential
insights always will have to some degree
that rebound effect why
because your brain well i don't agree
with all of the sort of model in
cognitive sciences called predictive
processing your brain is
part of it is because they should be
talking about anticipation not just
prediction
your brain is an anticipation machine
it's always trying to predict the
environment
and prepare itself that's what i mean by
anticipation and do that a highly
complex and deeply inter-penetrating
coupled manner it's an anticipation
machine and so your brain
loves familiarity and remember what i
talked about including specificity
it's not just familiarity out there it's
familiarity in here
in your processing your brain prefers
familiar unhappiness to surprising
happiness
and you go but i like surprise parties
yeah but notice how
there you get all the people around you
who love you it's in a very safe
situation
right there's cake and there's good like
there's all kinds of stuff dude like oh
that's okay
um so generally when we get an insight
an existential insight that
is going to take us into an unfamiliar
world and an unfamiliar sense of self it
has that potential
there's a part of it that our brain sort
of goes uh i don't like that
i don't like that there's anxiety around
that
lack of familiarity and there's an
attempt to let's pull you back
let's pull you back
and of course that's ultimately part of
the way your brain is adapted because
it's
trying to always calibrate between
accommodating
to what's the new but also assimilating
to what is familiar and it's always
trying to toggle between them
and so that your observations i think
are deeply correct dean
okay everyone i think we got to uh some
questions we'll try and get through
another bunch again tomorrow
um i want to thank you all for joining
it's always wonderful to be here
i want to thank my dear friend and
technomagemar i want to thank my
beloved son jason who's learning a lot
behind the scenes and learning and doing
a lot behind the scenes
increasingly more so i want
uh to ask you all if possible to please
subscribe to this channel to be notified
of the next video
also to um
you'll find links to the uh the lecture
series awakening from the meaning crisis
and the dialogue series voices with
raveki
and which these themes are discussed at
length
related to relevant other themes
and situated in with it within a more
encompassing framework that aspires to
responding to the meaning crisis
um and awakening wisdom please invite
others who might benefit by sharing this
series
the discord server is there please join
the discord server to chat with others
uh to practice with others to discuss
and reflect with others
i know they do a couple sits every day i
know they're doing some lectio together
some moving practices there's yoga
there's a bunch of things on offer there
um and help shape the discord server
it's going to have noise in it it's
going to it's right it need it needs
help and guidance to shape itself
uh to something that is
optimally set uh for carrying a
community
forward in joint and in individual
aspiration
reminder we're doing this every weekday
morning at 9 30 eastern time there will
be no class
on monday there will be no class on
monday
because it is a holiday there will be no
class on monday because it is a holiday
um i will tell you tomorrow what day
we're going to move um
dharma day what day we'll move it to in
the week i'm coordinating things with
jason and nmr
so i'll let you know it might be a good
idea if possible if you're not on it
already
for as many of you as possible to follow
me on twitter
uh because then it would be easy for me
to send out announcements to people
very broadly and very quickly um
all right so i think um
uh i think that discord server will be
offering the meditation classes even on
monday because
a lot of people in the states etc so uh
please join the discord server there
uh for uh for saying it all right
everyone please remember that continuity
of practice
and a compassion for yourself is more
important
than sheer quantity of practice or any
kind of
you know puritanical perfectionism
you're holding yourself to
befriend yourself remember that there is
no
enemy worse than your own mind and body
but there is no friend no ally no true
companion on your path
better in your own mind and body relaxed
unto yourselves
and to each other take good care
everyone and i'll see you tomorrow